Guide to the Alice M. Monk papers M2033
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Alice Monk papers
circa 1910-1952
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Monk, Alice M.
Van Saun, Matthew
M2033
1 linear foot (2 boxes)
Biographical note
Alice Maud Monk was a Presbyterian missionary in Japan for 37 years, and taught at the Girls School in Happoro, Hokkaido, Japan (JoGakko School and perhaps others as well). Daughter of John Sherwin Monk and Ella M. Sanford, she had three sisters: Florence E., Laura E., and Clara Louise. Alice returned to the United States in 1941. In 1905, she came to Hokusei Girls’ School. One year after her arrival in Japan, Monk helped consolidate the educational program and worked for its expansion. Monk became principal in 1915, and in the same year the Ministry of Education recognized the school. A new site for the school was obtained in 1924; a dormitory and a missionary house were built in 1926.
Scope and Contents
Materials include a personal notebook that Monk kept from 1922-1941, correspondence, photos, print ephemera. In addition there are: 7 issues of “The Northern Star” illustrated publications (on rice paper) from the English Dept. Hokusei JoGakko, Sapporo, Hokkaido (March 1937, Jan. 1940, Feb. 1940, June 1940, July 1940, and two June 1941). P1937 Northern Star Girls’ High School yearbook (water damage); leather planner with assorted Japanese newspapers, booklets, written in Japanese (one glossy booklet has black & white photos of the school, students, & classes, and Monk appears on page 3); Assorted University Extension Conservatory exam papers for Mrs. Monk.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by Stanford University Libraries in 2015.
Monk, Alice M.
- Directory of student names, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Stationery and calling cards (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Newspaper clippings (Japanese) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Pamphlet (Japanese) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Pages of Japanese text, annotated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- University Extension Conservatory, Chicago, Ill.: Harmony lessons, various numbers (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Supplement to the International Gleanings from Japan, no. 3-4, 1931; Explanations of twelve selector colour pictures Japan her land & life; pamphlet in Japanese (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Various small religious publications; 2 Messageries maritimes: Escale de Hong-Kong 1929 and ship passenger list Ligne de Chine & Japon departing 28 Avril 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Northern Star Girls' High School, 1887-1937, Sapporo, Japan (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Class photograph September 19, 1910 at Mrs. Michida's (Flat-box 2, Folder 1)
- Class photograph (Flat-box 2, Folder 2)
- The Northern Star: March 1937, January 1940, February 1940, June 1940, July 1940, June 1941 (Flat-box 2, Folder 3)